WARNING: IMAGES OF SUICIDE AND SELF-HARM.
NAPOLEON BONAPARTE
THE MASTER STRATEGIST OF THE 19TH CENTURY
ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF SOLITUDE
Aureliano asked Arcadio
to get Macondo in better shape
than how he'd left it.
Arcadio had a very unique interpretation
of this request.
He's dressed like a general.
People of Macondo!
The true essence of Macondo
must be restored by all of us!
Yes! We must do it together!
I have decided…
that as of right this second,
all men are required by law to report
for military service at the station.
Everyone will have to wear the bandana
that my soldiers will hand out right now!
Every house,
every establishment, every wall
will bear the same red color of our party!
Our party, huh? Hmm.
Listen. It's one thing for us to stand up
against the Conservative violence,
but our people have been free
since before you were even born!
That's true. That's true!
What would your son say then, Matilde?
Is he not risking his life out there,
with the colonel?
With this bandana around his arm too, hmm?
Everyone standing here has seen
what these bastards are willing to do!
So ask yourself,
what are we willing to do for ourselves?
Whatever is necessary, Catarino!
Because this is our town!
-This is our territory!
-Yeah!
To the Liberals! Whoo!
Yeah!
-Long live the Liberal Party!
-To the Liberals!
-I wonder what Úrsula thinks, Father.
-She won't think anything.
Arcadio is still a child,
and what he's doing
is simply a show, that's all.
I don't know, Father.
I don't think he's a child anymore.
Don't listen to him.
His bark is worse than his bite.
One side each.
Let's go.
-Come on, Father.
-What are you doing?
-Hey!
-Amen!
Get him! stop it! Please!
-Lock it. Let's go!
-No, please!
-Stay still, Father!
-Bye!
Hey, stay in there! Go, go, go!
Careful, man. Watch your hand.
-Open the door! Hey!
-Hey! Yeah!
Open the door!
What are you doing?!
I'm leaving.
Rebeca's firm character
and the voracity of her stomach,
absorbed José Arcadio's boundless energy.
He went from being a lazy womanizer
to a massive work animal.
It was said that he had begun
by plowing his own yard
and that he continued
straight ahead into neighboring lands,
knocking down fences and ranches
until he seized
the best plots of land around.
Morning.
That your house over there?
Mm-hmm.
How may I help you?
How, uh… how much do you pay for all this?
-Pay?
-To who exactly?
This land belongs to us.
According to who?
And who are you to come here
and ask me about all that?
José Arcadio Buendía.
The eldest son of the founder of Macondo.
Well then,
your old man knows
that we have lived in this home
since long before the awful insomnia.
It looks to me like you appropriated land
that belongs to my family,
after my father went insane.
And you never paid him anything.
Or am I wrong?
Those bastards aren't just murdering us.
They're humiliating us.
I don't know how many weapons they have.
We'll do as you say, Colonel.
Mm…
Colonel Carmona,
I'm Colonel Aureliano Buendía.
We're gonna get you outta here.
Thank you, Colonel.
Liberals!
Come on! Come on!
You have to get Carmona! Go get Carmona!
They need me as a hostage, Colonel!
Save your people!
Colonel! Today's not the day, Colonel!
Soldier! Today's not the day!
I'll come back for you
as soon as I have more men.
You have my word.
-Aureliano!
-So stay strong.
Retreat, soldiers!
-Let's go!
-Attack!
Let's go! Let's go!
Visbal! Visbal!
We had them, my friend.
We have to keep fighting.
Take it easy, brother.
Throwing blows
isn't gonna help you recover.
Come on, drink.
Aureliano, what are we gonna do?
Trying to leave camp like this
is pointless. It's going to be impossible.
I have to go and find help.
Alone?
There must be a camp of Conservatives
in every town from here to San Juan.
Yes, but my odds are better if I go alone.
He's right, brother.
Evening. I need your help, sir.
You don't need to do this, sir.
Father!
-No!
-Get back inside!
What's going on with you?
Catarino, give me that bottle.
What did he say?
He says that I have to pay him
for the ten years
that I have been working the land
we live on… or he'll shoot me.
Wait a minute.
The same boy, the same José Arcadio
that took his clothes off
right there at that table
and raffled himself off to women?
The same exact one. That's him.
We have to talk to Arcadio,
see if he knows that.
Mm. That's the right thing to do.
What's he gonna do about it?
Chase him around with his imaginary spear?
Look, Anibal.
Remember this is
Macondo's civil and military chief
we're referring to.
No, I'm talking about
a young boy who's gone mad
and walks around in a costume
saying all sorts of nonsense.
Why do you pay so much attention
to that boy, anyway?
The reason I pay attention
is because he is the one
that Colonel Aureliano Buendía
put in charge.
Now, if you don't respect
what Arcadio says,
does that mean
you don't respect Aureliano either?
What's the matter, my friend?
We gonna fight over this?
Tell me which side you're on,
and I'll tell you if we're fighting.
Well, we're on the same side.
Huh. All right, then.
Have a drink, my friend.
Ready!
Aim your guns!
Fire!
Come on, boys. Let's go! Again!
Ready!
Aim!
Arcadio! Catarino!
-Goddamn it!
-Son of a…
You can't just shoot!
You have to listen to orders!
-What's going on?
-I need to speak to you.
You have to train those dogs.
-I'm joking.
-Don't you dare touch my dogs.
They won't calm down.
To what do we owe this pleasure?
How are you, sister?
You're our very first visitor.
It's hot. Can I have something to drink?
I was hoping we could talk.
Have a seat.
I was on my way out. What's the matter?
I've been told about what you're doing
in the fields, and we need to discuss it.
I don't meddle in your affairs,
so why are you meddling in mine?
Unfortunately,
my position forces me
to meddle in everything.
Don't worry about it. You can relax.
I didn't come here for an explanation.
I came to legalize it for you.
No property has ever been
registered in this town.
Until now.
All you have to do
to become the owner of the land
is to sign this form right here.
Of course, we expect you to make
a small contribution to our office.
Don't worry. You could pay us
with what you earn from your plots.
That's up to you.
That's certainly something
I won't meddle in.
Wah!
"According to official sources,
the rebels have devastated
entire populations,
and all in the name of the Liberal Party."
Hmm.
And where's the part that says
how the Conservatives got here?
They just forget to include that?
And you're still here.
Tied up, like a madman.
But I'm glad your here, at least.
Hmm.
Who knows what you'd do
if you had any idea
of what's been going on.
Hmm.
What's wrong? What is it? Visitación!
Look at me. Pietro! Pietro! Here!
-I'm coming, what's going on?
-Look at me, Visitación!
-Visitación!
-Help me, son.
What are you doing here, son?
I think this is the place
where your mother realized
we had been moving around in circles.
I have this peculiar feeling
I've already been through all of this.
You know,
I never actually told your mother
that I never stopped being lost.
As if I haven't been over
at his house since he was a baby.
As if I wasn't,
for all intents and purposes,
part of his family.
And now he's building
that colossal house all of a sudden.
With whose money?
With ours.
Let's see. What does it say?
It says that his office
actually has the right
to 15% of every drink I sell.
Women must pay 20%
for every customer they fuck,
and that you must pay 8%
of your total earnings.
But why is our percentage higher?
Mm…
Oh, the things my dear friend José Arcadio
would do
if he wasn't tied up
to that old chestnut tree.
-Just what we needed.
-No.
Gentlemen!
Hello.
Hey, Catarino.
Why don't you bring over some rum
for, uh… for us and, um,
some water for Franco, please?
Thank you.
Are you gonna pay the full amount,
or should I deduct what I have to pay you?
You don't have to
pay me anything, Catarino.
What you're paying for is the war.
Or how do you think
it'll be financed? With will?
And here I was thinking
you were on our side.
Hey, where's the music?
Or can't you afford that anymore?
Come on. Of course he can.
There will always be music in here.
♪ One of my dear old friends ♪
♪ Begs for rum at this cantina ♪
♪ Stealing money from the women ♪
-♪ Sending all our men to war-- ♪
-Sing something else?
I don't know.
Something happier, something nice.
All right, give me a second.
Cut it out!
Forgive me.
So there won't always be music after all.
Brother! Aníbal!
Anibal!
He's dead.
Arcadio!
I just wanna talk to him. Arcadio!
-Pilar, what's the matter?
-Santa Sofía, I need to talk to Arcadio.
What the hell is the matter with you?
I asked the cards about you.
I don't have time for this.
Listen to me!
No one cares about you
more than I do. Believe me.
In the future,
a woman will try to give you advice.
You have to listen to her.
Are you done?
He needs to stay alert.
Please tell him.
Easy now.
I promise you're not the first
Liberal soldier to find refuge here.
Thank you for everything,
but my men are waiting for me.
Where are you going?
There are men everywhere
trying to find Liberals like you.
Listen, ma'am,
I don't have time.
I need to find reinforcements.
I'll take you to someone who can help you.
But not before sunset.
We stay inside until then.
It's because of them that we do this.
There are hawks outside.
Wait! Wait! Stop!
He's one of us.
-I'm Colonel Aureliano Buendía!
-Let him in.
I lost several of my men
when trying to rescue Colonel Carmona.
And those of us who survived
are mostly severely wounded now
and in need of something to eat.
I have heard rumors about you,
Colonel Buendía.
I'm Colonel Gregorio Stevenson.
Pleasure to meet you, sir.
Pleasure, sir.
When are we leaving then?
We leave when you say so.
My friend!
Where's Visbal?
It wasn't just our men
that the Conservatives killed, Gerineldo.
They're doing the same thing all over.
We need to put a stop to this now.
This sorry excuse
of a government must fall.
Look, I know that the army
has more resources than we do…
but we have something
those other men don't!
We have a fighting spirit
and the greatest debt of honor
to our fallen other soldiers!
But our priority is to save our people.
Otherwise, what are
any of us fighting for?
And I don't know
if you feel the same way I do…
but we musn't stop fighting,
not until we make
those sons of bitches pay us all back
every last single drop of blood
that our men have shed for us!
-Long live Colonel Buendía!
-To Buendía!
And long live the Liberal Party!
Long live the Liberals!
-The Liberals are coming!
-Liberals approaching!
For the Liberal Party!
"Úrsula. Mother."
"I won't deny that sometimes,
we suffer from hunger."
"I have not stopped being afraid,
and I am getting used to
burying my friends…"
"…but there is a profound feeling
that keeps us going."
"Maybe it's because we're
brushing against death
or because we are
fighting for what is just."
"I don't know."
"But the truth is
that nothing has ever felt more right
than being with those who are unwilling
to bend a knee to anyone."
"I am sorry I cannot tell you
where I'm headed
or how long it'll be
before we meet again."
"But I can assure you that now,
more than ever,
I am awake."
Ah!
I won't ever see my boy again, Visitación.
Either a bullet or starvation
will get him.
What's wrong, child?
What is it?
It won't be starvation.
Ma'am,
please do me this favor,
and bring Father Nicanor.
I need to see him.
Father Nicanor!
Oh! God bless you, Úrsula.
Dear God, Father. Who did this to you?
Arcadio.
Arcadio!
Don't you dare put your hands on me!
Don't even think of touching me!
Where are you? Where is he?!
Good afternoon to you too.
Ready to pay your taxes?
Who the hell do you think you are?
The civil and military authority
of our people.
When Aureliano finds out
that you murdered Aníbal
and that you've
been taking advantage of this town,
he'll have you shot.
And I'll be first to celebrate.
You're a disgrace to the Buendía name.
Make no mistake, Arcadio.
It's one thing to fear
and another to respect.
Úrsula.
I'm honored that I'm not a Buendía.
You made that quite clear.
Just let her go.
After the confusion
of Rebeca's vehement fondling,
Pietro Crespi found love in Amaranta.
I know that park in Firenze very well.
It's full of beautiful flowers.
Amaranta,
I know it hasn't been that long…
but Úrsula has already
given us her blessing.
And besides,
I think Aureliano José deserves a family.
Hmm.
And I would love nothing more in the world
than to take you to see Italy.
Amaranta Buendía…
will you marry me?
It doesn't have to be right away.
Not this coming month or year or ever.
If you really love me, Pietro,
don't come back to this house again.
♪ Where are you? ♪
♪ Where are you ♪
♪ My beloved? ♪
♪ Come console ♪
♪ The soul ♪
♪ Come ♪
♪ My beloved ♪
♪ Where… ♪
Macondo woke up
in a sort of angelic stupor…
caused by the sounds
of a string instrument…
…the world was not worthy of.
And the most adoring voice
the Earth could ever conceive.
♪ Come ♪
♪ Come console ♪
♪ The soul ♪
Perpetual light
shine upon him.
Eternal rest,
grant unto him, O Lord.
Let perpetual light
shine upon him.
Eternal rest,
grant unto him, O Lord.
And let
perpetual light shine upon him.
Eternal rest,
grant unto him, O Lord.
And let
perpetual light shine upon him.
Eternal rest,
grant unto him, O Lord.
And let
perpetual light shine upon him.
Eternal rest,
grant unto him, O Lord.
And let
perpetual light shine upon him.
Eternal rest,
grant unto him, O Lord.
And let
perpetual light shine upon him.
Eternal rest,
grant unto him, O Lord.
And let
perpetual light shine upon him.
Eternal rest,
grant unto him, O Lord.
And let
perpetual light shine upon him.
Eternal rest,
grant unto him, O Lord.
And let
perpetual light shine upon him.
Úrsula abandoned her forever.
Ready! Aim guide!
Fire!
Ready!
Aim! Fire!
Aim!
Fire!
Ready!
Aim! Fire!
-Mr. Moscote.
-Catarino.
Listen, since the incident with Aníbal,
no one wants to go out.
Musicians fled to neighboring towns,
and the women in my establishment
are starving.
Well, how is that my concern?
I mean, you're the mayor, aren't you?
If you don't put an end
to Arcadio's nonsense, then who will?
No, Catarino.
I'm nothing.
But now you all have what you wanted.
A Liberal paradise.
Well, go enjoy it.
Look at what we have come to,
José Arcadio Buendía.
Look at our empty house.
Just the two of us,
as it was when it all began.
Our children,
a true disgrace to the family name.
Don't listen to what I tell you.
God wanted
Rebeca and José Arcadio to get married,
and they're both very happy.
And Aureliano… seems like our son
has become a real hero out there.
Look.
He sent us a letter not long ago.
Do you want me to read it?
He hasn't written to us in months.
Úrsula!
Do something, please! Do something!
You continue to defy the law!
Say what you will about me!
But we will always be listening to you!
Ready!
Aim!
I dare you, you bastard!
-Don't push it, Úrsula.
-Or what?
You'll kill me as well?
Do it. Just do it!
I'd rather die than cry the shame
of having raised a fucking monster!
I said get out of the way!
Murderer! Murderer!
Can't you see
that you're terrorizing your own people?!
Enough!
The Colonel entrusted me
as the civil and military chief
of Macondo!
Aureliano is dead now!
What are you gonna do, huh?
You're worthless, Arcadio.
Listen closely.
Everybody will paint their house
the way they see fit.
Next time you try to extort
or kill someone else in this town…
I will find out.
Come on!
Úrsula. Úrsula. Úrsula.
There, there. It's going to be all right.
From that day on,
she was the one who ruled the town.
But in spite of her fortitude,
she still wept over her unfortunate fate.
Has no one paid?
No one, boss.
Excuse me, boss.
-A woman's here to see you.
-Franco, I don't want visitors.
Yes, sir.
Move back!
Easy.
Sir, I'm Colonel Gregorio Stevenson.
Colonel Buendía sent me here
in order to deliver a message.
The Conservative army is on its way.
They're near.
The colonel orders you
to surrender when they arrive.
-Take him away.
-Come here, you liar.
Listen to me! Please don't!
There are over 500--
-That's enough!
-They carry heavy artillery!
-Resisting will lead to a massacre!
-Let's go.
Do as the colonel says!
Do as a dead man says?
The Colonel isn't dead, Arcadio!
We've been fighting
alongside General Medina for months.
I can prove that he sent me
if you give me a chance to show you.
The colonel sold
hundreds of those fish pendants
long before the war started.
Confine him.
There's no time left! They're too close!
The colonel is preparing
a counteroffensive
to regain control of the town!
Arcadio, listen to me!
-Listen to me! They're almost here!
-Come on.
Arcadio! Arcadio!
Leave me alone.
Those Conservatives are
a bunch of fairies…
…sending a spy dressed as a woman.
A woman?
There was a man dressed like a woman.
He was saying
that the Conservatives are coming.
Arcadio! Arcadio, what's happening?
Come on, boss! Let's go!
Run! Run!
Take cover! Take cover!
Whoa!
Yah!
No!
No, no, no, no, no!
Oh!
Help me!
Franco! Franco!
-We have to go!
-To the station! To the station!
Run! Run! Go! Go! Go!
Make way!
Oh!
Arcadio!
Run, boss! Go! Run!
Ah!
Arcadio! Set me free!
Spare me the indignity
of dying in restrains
dressed up as a woman!
Free me! Free me!
Uh!
-Uh!
Oh!
-Ah!
Ah!
Oh!
Fire!
Ah!
Hurry! Hurry!
Uh!
Hey!
Be quiet. Be quiet.
No! Get out, you piece of shit!
Get out! Get out!
Please don't! Don't!
Moscote, you need
to do something!
Moscote! You need to stop this massacre!
-And what do you expect me to do now?
-Make them stop firing.
-Tell them to cease fire!
-I have no power--
No!
Apolinar!
Arcadio!
Come with me! Come on! Run!
Take shelter!
Get to safety!
-Run! Come on, let's go!
-Hurry, let's get to the house!
-Come on, Arcadio!
-Arcadio, for God's sake!
Stop this madness!
Stop right there!
I'm Captain Roque Carnicero!
We didn't come for you, lady.
But our orders are clear.
Move out of the way.
Arcadio.
Don't!
-Don't you touch them.
-Soldiers!
Let's go!
In the last two hours
of his life,
Arcadio thought about his people
without sentimentality.
Confronting a hard reckoning,
he began to understand how much
he truly loved those he had hated most.
Any last words from you?
Tell my wife
that our little girl
should be named Úrsula.
And if the baby is a boy,
he shall be called José Arcadio.
Not after his uncle, but his grandfather.
Attention!
Get ready!
Take aim!
You bastards!
-Long live the Liberal Party!
-Soldiers, fire!
BASED ON THE NOVEL BY
GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ